Guide to the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Normal Separation-Individuation Studies, 1959-1977; Series II; 54.5 linear feet (67 boxes)
  - Duplicate Notebook Material
    - Billy N.
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1972-1975 (Box 69, Folder 930)
    - Brian C.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 69, Folder 931)
      - Observations, 1963, 1964 (Box 69, Folder 932)
    - Christopher A.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 69, Folder 933)
      - Interim summary, 1973 (Box 69, Folder 934)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1965, 1966, 1976 (Box 69, Folder 935)
    - Christopher H.-Once only material, undated (Box 69, Folder 936)
    - Claire A.
      - Once only material, Observations, 1961-1963 (Box 69, Folder 937)
      - Area observations, 1962, 1963 (Box 69, Folder 938)
      - Tests, 1961, 1962 (Box 69, Folder 939)
      - Intervening summaries, 1963-1967 (Box 69, Folder 940)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1973 (Box 69, Folder 941)
    - Claudia C.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 69, Folder 942)
      - Observations, 1966, 1967 (Box 69, Folder 943)
      - Four topics (brief statements), 1968, 1969 (Box 70, Folder 944)
      - Intervening summaries, 1972 (Box 70, Folder 945)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1973, 1974, 1977 (Box 70, Folder 946)
    - Deborah J.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 70, Folder 947)
      - Observations, 1966, 1967 (Box 70, Folder 948)
      - Intervening summaries, 1966 (Box 70, Folder 949)
      - Ten questions (key statements), 1965 (Box 70, Folder 950)
      - Four topics (brief statements), 1968, 1969 (Box 70, Folder 951)
      - Intervening summary, 1967, 1968 (Box 70, Folder 952)
      - Follow-up and summaries, undated (Box 70, Folder 953)
    - Evan E.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 70, Folder 954)
      - Observations, 1966, 1967 (Box 70, Folder 955)
      - Interim summary, 1966-1972 (Box 70, Folder 956)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1973 (Box 70, Folder 957)
    - Gillian S., undated
      - Follow-up and summaries (Box 70, Folder 958)
    - Hadley S.
      - Observations, 1965, 1966 (Box 70, Folder 959)
      - Four topics (brief statements), 1968, 1969 (Box 70, Folder 960)
      - Tests, 1964, 1967, 1974 (Box 70, Folder 961)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1973, 1974, 1976 (Box 70, Folder 962)
    - Helen L.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 70, Folder 963)
      - Observations, 1966 (Box 70, Folder 964)
      - Follow-up and summaries, undated (Box 70, Folder 965)
    - Jennifer L.-Tests, 1962 (Box 70, Folder 966)
    - Jonathan A.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 70, Folder 967)
      - Observations, 1961-1966 (Box 70, Folder 968)
      - Follow-up and summary, 1966, 1972, 1973, 1976 (Box 70, Folder 969)
    - Malcolm S.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 70, Folder 970)
      - Observations, 1964, 1965 (Box 70, Folder 971)
    - Michael S.
      - Once only materials; observations, 1966 (Box 71, Folder 972)
    - Follow-up, 1973 (Box 71, Folder 973)
    - Paul C.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 71, Folder 974)
      - Observations, 1966, 1967 (Box 71, Folder 975)
      - Interim summary, 1966, 1967 (Box 71, Folder 976)
      - Follow-up and summary, 1973 (Box 71, Folder 977)
    - Scott E.
      - Observations, 1963, 1964 (Box 71, Folder 978)
      - Once only material, undated (Box 71, Folder 979)
      - Follow-up and summary, 1973, 1976 (Box 71, Folder 980)
    - Susan S.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 71, Folder 981)
      - Observations, 1965, 1966 (Box 71, Folder 982)
      - Intervening summary, 1972 (Box 71, Folder 983)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1973-1975 (Box 71, Folder 984)
    - Sylvia C.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 71, Folder 985)
      - Observations, 1964 (Box 71, Folder 986)
      - Four topics, 1969 (Box 71, Folder 987)
      - Intervening summaries, 1966-1969 (Box 71, Folder 988-989)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1973 (Box 71, Folder 990)
    - Tommy A.
      - Once only material, undated (Box 71, Folder 991)
      - Observations, 1965, 1966 (Box 71, Folder 992)
      - Four topics, 1968, 1969 (Box 71, Folder 993)
      - Interim summaries, 1967, 1970 (Box 71, Folder 994)
      - Follow-up and summaries, 1973 (Box 71, Folder 995)
      - Mother's classification, undated (Box 71, Folder 996)
  - Methodology
    - Field foundation project, 1959, n. d. (Box 72, Folder 997)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1961, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 998)
    - Tentative research plan, 1961 (Box 72, Folder 999)
    - Rating scales and procedures, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 1000)
    - Manual of monthly collection, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 1001)
    - Rating scales and procedures, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 1002)
    - Staff meeting notes, 1961 (Box 72, Folder 1003)
    - Research meeting/conference notes, 1961, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 1004)
    - Evening meeting notes, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 1005)
    - "A Methodological Overview", 1961, 1962 (Box 72, Folder 1006-1008)
    - General, 1964, 1965 (Box 73, Folder 1009)
    - Ratings, 1961-1963 (Box 73, Folder 1010-1011)
    - General, 1964-1969 (Box 73, Folder 1012-1017)
    - General, 1969 (Box 74, Folder 1018)
    - Research plans, 1969, 1970 (Box 74, Folder 1019)
  - Notebook-McDevitt
    - Gender Identity
      - Claudia C., 1975 (Box 74, Folder 1020)
      - Hadley S., 1975 (Box 74, Folder 1021)
      - Helen L., 1974 (Box 74, Folder 1022)
    - Female development
      - Deborah J., 1975 (Box 74, Folder 1023)
      - Mandy N., 1975 (Box 74, Folder 1024)
      - Susan S., 1975 (Box 74, Folder 1025)
    - Summary material
      - Deborah J., undated (Box 74, Folder 1026-1028)
  - Research Conference Minutes
    - General, 1967-1979 (Box 74, Folder 1029-1031)
  - Schedules:
    See also: box 74, folder 1018
    - Testing, Undated (Box 74, Folder 1032)
    - Observations, 1963-1968 (Box 74, Folder 1033)
    - FOLIO (Box 74A)
  - Microfiche
    - Set 1, undated (Box 75)
      Area observations Coordinated observations Film notes and observations Reduced data, narrative and general remarks
    - Set 2, undated (Box 75)
    - Set 3, undated (Box 75)
      Area observations Coordinated observations Film notes and observations(2) Reduced data, narrative and general remarks
    - Set 4, undated (Box 76)
  - Microfilm
    - Area observations, undated (Box 77)
      Coordinated observations Film notes Reduced data
    - Observations (Box 78)
    - Card Index, undated (Box 78)
      Amy Cl., Amy Co., Ben J., Brian, Chris, Chris H., Claudia, Debbie, Evan, Gillian, Hadley, Jennifer, Malcolm, Mandy, Michael, Paul, Scott, Sylvia, Tommy
- Videotapes, 1962-; Series III; 12 linear feet (31 boxes)
  This series is arranged in three subseries: Longitudinal, Condensed, and Horizontal and Cross Sectional films. Within the Longitudinal film, the videotapes are arranged alphabetically by the child's first name. The Condensed films and the Horizontal and Cross-Sectional films have been retained in the original order established by the Foundation. A two part index to these videotapes is available in Box 79.
  - Separation-Individuation Study
    - Index-part 1, undated (Box 79, Folder 1034)
    - Index-part 2, undated (Box 79, Folder 1035)
    - Longitudinal
      - A1 Amy C1./Alma, undated (Box 80, Folder 1036)
      - B1-B2 Amy Co./Anna, undated (Box 80, Folder 1037-1038)
      - B3 Amy Co./Anna, undated (Box 81, Folder 1039)
      - C1-C2 Benjamin/Bernie, undated (Box 81, Folder 1040-1041)
      - C3 Benjamin/Bernie, undated (Box 82, Folder 1042)
      - D1 Brian/Barney, undated (Box 82, Folder 1043)
      - D2 Brian/Barney (16 months), undated (Box 82, Folder 1044)
      - El-E3 Chris A./Charles, undated (Box 83, Folder 1045-1047)
      - Fl-F3 Claudia/Linda, undated (Box 84, Folder 1048-1050)
      - F4-F5 Claudia/Linda, undated (Box 85, Folder 1051-1052)
      - G1 Debbie/Donna, undated (Box 85, Folder 1053)
      - G2-G4 Debbie/Donna, undated (Box 86, Folder 1054-1056)
      - H1-H2 Evan/Emmett, undated (Box 87, Folder 1057-1058)
      - I1 Freddy/Frank, undated (Box 87, Folder 1059)
      - J1/J2 Gillian/Gloria, undated (Box 88, Folder 1060)
      - K1/K2 Hadley/Harriet; part 1, undated (Box 88, Folder 1061)
      - K2/K3 Hadley/Harriet; part 2, part 1, undated (Box 88, Folder 1062)
      - K3/K4 Hadley/Harriet; part 2, part 1, undated (Box 89, Folder 1063)
      - L1 Jennifer/Junie/Janie (Box 89, Folder 1064)
      - L2 Jennifer/Julie (Box 89, Folder 1065)
      - M1/M2-M2/M3 Malcolm/Matthew, undated (Box 90, Folder 1066-1067)
      - N1/N2 Amanda/Margie; part 1, undated (Box 90, Folder 1068)
      - N2/N3 Amanda/Margie; part 2, undated (Box 91, Folder 1069)
      - O1/O2-O2/O3 Michael/Mark, undated (Box 91, Folder 1070-1071)
      - 04 Michael/Mark (Box 92, Folder 1072)
      - Pl/P2 Paul/Peter; part 1, undated (Box 92, Folder 1073)
      - P2/P3 Paul/Peter; part 2, part 1, undated (Box 92, Folder 1074)
      - P3/P4/P5 Paul/Peter; part 2, part 1, part 1, undated (Box 93, Folder 1075)
      - P5 Paul/Peter; part 2 (Box 93, Folder 1076)
      - Q1/Q2 Scott/Stuart/Sam; part 1, undated (Box 93, Folder 1077)
      - Q2/Q3 Scott/Stuart/Sam; part 2, undated (Box 94, Folder 1078)
      - Q4 Scott/Stuart, undated (Box 94, Folder 1079)
      - R1/R2 Sylvia/Susan; part 1, undated (Box 94, Folder 1080)
      - R2/R3 Sylvia/Susan; part 2, undated (Box 95, Folder 1081)
      - R4 Sylvia/Susan, undated (Box 95, Folder 1082)
      - S1/S2 Tommy/Teddy; part 1, undated (Box 95, Folder 1083)
      - S2/S3 Tommy/Teddy; part 2, undated (Box 96, Folder 1084)
      - S4 Tommy/Teddy (Box 96, Folder 1085)
      - T1 William/Billy/Tommy, Christopher H./Carl Misc. (Box 96, Folder 1086)
      - U1 Vivian/David//Va/Daniel (Box 97, Folder 1087)
      - V1 Susan/Claire Sarah/Cathy (Box 97, Folder 1088)
      - W2 Jonathan/Jay (Box 97, Folder 1089)
    - Condensed
      - Ml-M3 Malcolm/Matthew, undated (Box 98, Folder 1090)
      - El-E3 Chris A./Charles, undated (Box 98, Folder 1091)
      - S1-S4 Tommy/Teddy, undated (Box 98, Folder 1092)
      - Q1-Q4 Scott/Stuart, undated (Box 99, Folder 1093)
      - O1-O4 Michael/Mark, undated (Box 99, Folder 1094)
      - P1-P5 Paul/Peter, undated (Box 99, Folder 1095)
      - F1-F5 Claudia/Linda, undated (Box 100, Folder 1096)
      - K1-K4 Hadley/Harriet, undated (Box 100, Folder 1097)
      - K4 Hadley/Harriet, undated (Box 100, Folder 1098)
      - D1-D2 Brian/Barney (Box 100, Folder 1098)
      - B1-B3 Amy Co./Anna, undated (Box 101, Folder 1099)
      - R1-R3 Sylvia/Susan, undated (Box 101, Folder 1100)
      - G1-G4 Donna, undated (Box 101, Folder 1101)
      - N1-N3 Amanda/Margie, undated (Box 102, Folder 1102)
      - C1-C3 Bernie/Benjamin, undated (Box 102, Folder 1103)
      - P Paul/Peter, undated (Box 102, Folder 1104)
      - F Claudia/Linda (Box 102, Folder 1104)
      - R Sylvia/Susan (Box 102, Folder 1104)
      - M1-M3 Matthew, undated (Box 103, Folder 1105)
      - El-E3 Charles (Box 103, Folder 1105)
      - Sl-S4 Teddy, undated (Box 103, Folder 1106)
      - Q1-Q4 Stuart, undated (Box 103, Folder 1107)
      - O1-O4 Mark, undated (Box 104, Folder 1108)
      - Pl-P4 Peter, undated (Box 104, Folder 1109)
      - Fl-F5 Linda, undated (Box 104, Folder 1110)
      - K1-K3 Harriet, undated (Box 105, Folder 1111)
      - Bl-B3 Anna (Box 105, Folder 1111)
      - R1-R4 Susan, undated (Box 105, Folder 1112)
      - G1-G4 Donna, undated (Box 105, Folder 1113)
      - Nl-N3 Margie (Box 105, Folder 1113)
    - Horizontal and Cross Sectional
      - C2 Mother-infant interaction #2; horizontal, undated (Box 106, Folder 1114-1115)
      - C2 Mother-infant interaction #2; cross-sectional, undated (Box 106, Folder 1116-1117)
      - C3 Interest in the world #3; horizontal, undated (Box 107, Folder 1118)
      - C3 Interest in the world #3; cross-sectional, undated (Box 107, Folder 1119)
      - C4 Differentiation #4; Horizontal and cross-sectional, undated (Box 107, Folder 1120)
      - C5 Stranger reaction #5; horizontal and cross-sectional, undated (Box 107, Folder 1121)
      - C6 Exploring his body; horizontal and cross-sectional, undated (Box 107, Folder 1121)
      - C8 Practicing #8; horizontal, undated (Box 108, Folder 1122)
      - C8 Practicing #8; cross sectional, undated (Box 108, Folder 1123)
      - C9 Rapprochment #9; horizontal, undated (Box 108, Folder 1124)
      - C9 Rapprochment #9; cross sectional, undated (Box 108, Folder 1125)
      - C10 Aggression and inhibition of aggression; horizontal and cross sectional, undated (Box 109, Folder 1126)
      - C11 Siblings #1; horizontal and cross-sectional, undated (Box 109, Folder 1127)
      - C12 Children with other children #12; horizontal and cross sectional (Box 109, Folder 1128)
      - C13 Relationships with other adults/fathers #13/#14, undated (Box 109, Folder 1129)
      - C18 Symbolization (Box 109, Folder 1129)
- Films, 1940s-1982; Series IV; 5 microfilm boxes; 5 medium shoeboxes; 17 paige boxes and 118 film cans
  This series is arranged chronologically by research project and within each project by type of film. The series contains materials from Mahler's tic syndrome studies, the investigation of symbiotic child psychosis, the separation-individuation studies, and the teaching and project films undertaken by the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation. The research films consist of original film footage, copy film footage, positive prints, and duplicate negative film documenting observations of the study children. The series contains both black and white and color film.
  - Tic Syndrome Studies: Original Film
    - "Tic Syndrome" and "Tic Symptoms" (Box 110)
      General note
      Henry 7 years, 9 months
      Jimmy, 12 years
      Eva, 9 years
      Juliette, 8 years
    - "Children with 'Tic Syndrome'" (Box 110)
      Morton, 11 years
      Henry, 7 years, 9 months
      Ted, 14.5 years
      Peter, 11 years and 15 years
    - Tic Film with Titles: A (Box 110)
      Henry, 7 years 9 months
    - Tic Film with Titles: B (2 copies)
      Arthur, 13 years
      Jackie, 6 years, 9 months
      Stevie, 6 years
      Danny and Henry
      - "Multiple Psychotic Tics" (Box 110)
      - "Symptomatic Mutiple Tics, statu nascendi in two little comedians," (Box 110)
      - "A Psychotic Child/Actor with Occasional Facial Tics," (Box 110)
    - Tic Film: C (Box 110)
      Helen
      B. Gr.
      Ralph, 25 years
      Johnnie, 11 years
    - Tic Film: D (Box 111)
      Norman, 9 years
      Helen, 21 years
    - Tic Film: E (Box 111)
      Dr. Luke's female patients.
      Henry
  - Tic Syndrome Studies: Copy Film
    - Tic Film with Titles: B (2 copies)
      - "Multiple Psychotic Tics" (Box 111)
      - "Symptomatic Multiple Tics, statu nascendi in two little comedians," (Box 111)
      - "A Psychotic Child Actor with Occasional Facial Tics," (Box 111)
    - Tic Film: C (Box 111)
    - Tic Film: D (Box 112)
    - Tic Film: E (Box 112)
    - Tic Film: Spliced Reels (Box 112)
    - Tic Film with Titles, copy A, 1979 June 30; 1 (Box 111)
  - Investigation of Symbiotic Child Psychosis: Original Film
    - Alan
      - Reel, 1961 March 17 (Box 112)
      - Reel # 1, 1962 May 18 (Box 112)
      - Reel # 2, 1962 May 18 (Box 112)
    - Abby
      - Reel, 1960 Spring (Box 112)
      - Reel # 1, 1961 March (Box 112)
      - Reel # 2, 1961 March (Box 113)
      - Reel # 1, 1961 March 8 (Box 113)
      - Reel # 2, 1961 March 8 (Box 113)
      - Reel # 1, 1961 May (Box 113)
      - Reel # 2, 1961 May (Box 113)
      - Reel # 1, 1961 June (Box 113)
      - Reel # 2, 1961 June (Box 113)
      - Psychotic Children: Abby, #1, original film, 1961 Mar 01; 1 (Box 112)
      - Psychotic Children: Abby, #2, original film, 1961 Mar 01; 1 (Box 112)
    - Bruce
      - Reel, 1961 December 14 (Box 114)
      - Reel, 1963 February 8 (Box 114)
      - Reel, 1964 February 26 (Box 114)
      - Reel # 1, 1964 March 2 (Box 114)
      - Reel # 2, 1964 March 2 (Box 114)
      - Reel # 3, 1964 March 2 (Box 114)
      - Reel # 1, 1964 April 24 (Box 114)
      - Reel # 2, 1964 April 24 (Box 114)
      - Reel, 1964 June 26 (Box 114)
    - David
      - 1960 Spring (Box 114)
    - Iris
      - Reels, 1962 May 24- May 31; 10 (Box 115)
      - Reels, 1962 June 7,14, 1963 June 10, 1963 September 30, 1963 October 9,16,30, 1964 February 4,10, 1964 March 2,9; 4 (Box 116)
    - Johnny
      - Reel # 1, 1962 April 23 (Box 116)
      - Reel # 2, 1962 April 23 (Box 116)
      - Reel # 3, 1962 April 23 (Box 116)
    - Mitchell
      - Reel, 1960 Spring (Box 116)
      - Reel # 1, 1961 March 15 (Box 116)
      - Reel # 2, 1961 March 15 (Box 116)
      - Reel, 1961 March 18 (Box 116)
      - Reel # 4, 1961 December 11 (Box 116)
      - Reel # 5, 1961 December 5 (Box 116)
      - Reel # R1, 1961 May 3 (Box 116)
      - Reel # R2, 1961 May 3 (Box 116)
      - Reel, 1962 November 29 (Box 116)
    - Mitchell and Abby
      - Reels, 1961-1962; 5 (Box 117)
    - Scott
      - Reel # 1, 1962 October 23 (Box 118)
      - Reel # 2, 1962 October 23 (Box 119)
    - Vicky
      - Reel # 1, 1961 June (Box 119)
      - Reel # 2, 1961 June (Box 119)
      - Reel, 1961 December 5 (Box 119)
      - Reel # 1, 1962 May 16 (Box 119)
      - Reel # 2, 1962 May 16 (Box 119)
      - Reel # 3, 1962 May 16 (Box 119)
      - Reel # 4, 1962 May 16 (Box 119)
      - Reel # 1, 1962 June 19 (Box 119)
      - Reel # 2, 1962 June 19 (Box 119)
      - Reel, 1963 April 13 (Box 119)
  - Investigation of Symbiotic Child Psychosis: Copy Film
    - Alan, 1961 March 17, 1962 May 18 (Box 120)
    - Abby, 1960 Spring, 1961 February 1, Mar, 1961 May-Jun; 5 (Box 120)
    - Bruce and David, spring 1960 - 1964 Jun 26; 7 (Box 121)
    - Bruce, 1963 Feb 08; 1 (Box 122)
    - David, 1960 Spring (2) (Box 122)
    - Iris, 1962 May 24,31, June 7,14, 1963 January 30, February 5, June 10, October 9,16,30, 1964 February 10, March 2; 6 (Box 122)
    - Johnny, 1962 April 23 (Box 122)
    - Mitchell, 1960 Spring, 1961 February 1, March 15, December 5,11, 1962 May 3,18; 3 (Box 122)
    - Scott, 1962 October 23 (Box 122)
    - Vicky, 1961 June, 1961 December 5, 1962 May 16, June 19, 1963 April 13; 3 (Box 122)
  - Separation-Individuation Studies: Original Film
    - Alma (Box A1)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3
    - Anna (Box B1–B3)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11
    - Bernie (Box C1–C3)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6 7,8
    - Barney (Box D1)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2
    - Barney [contains 2 rolls], 2 (Box D2)
      Original Reel No.: 3,4,5,6,7
    - Charles (Box E1–E3)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10
    - Linda (Box F1–F2)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6
    - Linda [includes F4], 2 (Box F3)
      Original Reel No.: 7,8,9
    - Linda (Box F5)
      Original Reel No.: 10,11,12
    - Donna (Box G1–G4)
    - Emmett [includes S2], 2 (Box H1)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4
    - Emmett (Box H2)
      Original Reel No.: 5,6,7
    - Freddie (Box I1)
    - Gloria (Box J1–J2)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12
    - Harriet (Box K1–K4)
    - Janie (Box L1–L2)
    - Matthew (Box M1–M3)
    - Margie (Box N1–N3)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8
    - Mark (Box O1–O4)
    - Peter [includes P2], 2 (Box P1)
    - Peter [includes P4], 2 (Box P3)
      Original Reel No.: 7,8,9,10,11
    - Peter [includes V1] (Box P5)
      Original Reel No.: 12,13,14
    - Stuart (Box Q1–Q4)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13
    - Susan (Box R1–R4)
    - Teddy (Box S1, Box S3–S4)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6 See also: Can No.: H-1
    - Teddy & Charles (Box T1)
    - Val & Daniel (Box U1)
    - Sarah & Cathy (Box P5)
      See also: Can No.: P-5
    - He-1,2 & Family visit & Jo (Box Z1)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,[1 reel]
  - Separation-Individuation Studies: Duplicate Negative Film
    - Alma (Box 1)
    - Anna (Box 2)
    - Anna (Box 4)
    - Bernie, 3 (Box 5–7)
    - Barney (Box 9–10)
    - Charles (Box 11–12)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,7,8,9,10,4,5,6
    - Linda (Box 13–17)
    - Donna (Box 19–21)
      Original Reel No.: 4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11
    - Emmett (Box 22–23)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7
    - Frank (Box 24)
    - Gloria (Box 25–26)
    - Harriet (Box 27–30)
    - Matthew (Box 33–35)
    - Margie (Box 36–38)
    - Mark (Box 39–42)
    - Peter (Box 43–47)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,14
    - Stuart (Box 48–51)
    - Susan (Box 52–55)
    - Teddy (Box 56, Box 58–59)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,7,8,9,10,11,12
    - Teddy & Charles (Box 60)
    - Val & Daniel (Box 61)
    - Sarah & Cathy (Box 62)
    - Heather & Family & Jay (Box 63)
  - Separation-Individuation Studies: Longitudinal Films, Positive Prints
    - Alma (Box 123, Reel A1)
    - Anna (Box 123, Reel B1-B3)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,7,8,9,10,11
    - Bernie, 3 (Box 123, Reel C1-C3)
    - Barney (Box 123, Reel D2-D3)
      Original Reel No.: 3,4,5,6,7,8
    - Anna (Box 123a, Reel B2)
      Original Reel No.: 4,5,6
    - Barney (Box 123a, Reel D1)
    - Charles, 3 (Box 124, Reel E1-E3)
    - Debbie, 1 (Box 124, Reel G1)
    - Linda, 4 (Box 127, Reel F1-F5)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,10,11,12
    - Donna, 3 (Box 124, Reel G1-G3)
      Original Reel No.: 4,5,6,7,8
    - Donna, 1 (Box 125, Reel G4)
      Original Reel No.: 9, 10, 11
    - Emmett, 2 (Box 125, Reel H1-H2)
    - Freddy, 1 (Box 125, Reel I1)
    - Gloria, 2 (Box 125, Reel J1-J2)
    - Harriet, 1 (Box 126, Reel K1)
    - Harriet (2 copies), 2 (Box 126, Reel K2-K3)
      Original Reel No.: 4,5,6,7,8,9
    - Harriet, 1 (Box 126, Reel K4)
    - Junie, 2 (Box 127, Reel L1-L2)
    - Matthew, 1 (Box 128, Reel M1)
    - Matthew, 1 (Box 128, Reel M2)
    - Matthew, 1 (Box 128, Reel M3)
    - Margie, 3 (Box 127, Reel N1-N3)
    - Mark, 4 (Box 128, Reel O1-O4)
    - Peter (Box 129, Reel P1)
    - Peter (Box 129a, Reel P2)
    - Peter (Box 130, Reel P3-P5)
      Original Reel No.: 7,8,9,10,11,12,12,13,14
    - Stuart (Box 131, Reel Q1-Q2)
    - Stuart (2 copies) (Box 131, Reel Q3-Q4)
      Original Reel No.: 7,8,9,10,11,12,13
    - Susan (Box 131, Reel R1)
    - Susan (Box 131, Reel R2)
      Original Reel No.: (2 copies)
    - Susan (Box 131, Reel R3-R5)
      Original Reel No.: 7,8,9,10,11,12,24-29
    - Teddy (Box 132, Reel S1-S4)
      Original Reel No.: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,11,12
    - Teddy & Charles (Box 133, Reel T1)
    - Val & Daniel (Box 133, Reel U1)
  - Uncoded Longitudinal Films
    - Anna (Box 134)
    - Barney (Box 134)
    - Charles (Box 134)
      Original Reel No.: 7,8,9,10
    - Emmett (Box 134)
    - Margie (Box 134)
      Original Reel No.: 6,7,8
    - Mark (Box 134)
      Original Reel No.: 10,11
    - Matthew (Box 134)
      Original Reel No.: 7,8,9,10,11,12
    - Susan (Box 134)
    - Teddy (Box 134)
      Original Reel No.: 11,12
    - Heather & Jay (Box 134)
    - Teddy & Charles (Box 134)
    - Val & Daniel (Box 134)
    - Teaching/Project Films (Box 134)
  - Teaching/Project Films
    - "Adaption & Defense in statunascendi " (Box 135)
      4 reels
    - "Annual Meeting of Masters children's center-film To set Them Free" (Box 135)
      1 reel
    - "Child Development Course--New York Psychoanalytic Institute" (Box 136)
      8 reels
    - "Development of Basic Moods" (Box 136)
      2 reels
    - "Highlights of Mother-Child Reaction" (Box 136)
    - "Mirror Reactions" (Box 137)
      5 reels
    - "Normal Separation-Individuation" (Box 137)
      3 reels
    - "Object Constancy" (Box 137)
    - "Psychological Birth of the Human Infant" (Box 138)
    - "Observational Data and Its Relevance" (Box 139)
- Additional Material, 1982, undated; Accession 1998-M-083
  Margaret S. Mahler Psych. Research Fndn-69
  This addition is comprised of 16 mm films.
  - "Iris," n. d.
    - Reel 1 (Box 1)
    - Reel 2 (Box 1)